# NIRMALADEVI VENKATARAMAN

**DATA ANALYST** 

Franklin, TN

6158393044

<u>LinkedIn Profile</u> GitHub Profile

nirmaladevivenkataraman@gmail.com

### **ABOUT ME**

Have 10 years' experience working with different databases in Data Warehouse (DW) platform. I am always excited about analyzing data in DW for the purpose of requirement analysis, troubleshooting data issues, ETL development and helping business users in their analysis. My interest in data eventually created my passion towards Data Analytics.

#### SKILLS

Data Analysis SQL (Postgres, MS SQL Server) Excel (Pivot, VLOOKUP) Power BI, Tableau, Python

## **DATA ANALYTICS EXPERIENCE**

### **Data Analytics Apprentice, Nashville Software School**

Nashville Software School is a nonprofit organization that prepares its students for careers in a variety of coding fields, including data analytics, through team-based, project-based learning. **Projects** 

- <u>Low Income and Elderly Assist Project</u>: Explored the data in excel, created numerous data reports using Excel Offset function. Worked in groups for building group dashboard, which improved my work experience in Agile methodology.
- <u>City Cemetery Burials</u>: Cleaned the data to get insights into common causes of death. Analysed for various scenarios to create a Marketing Dashboard.
- <u>Lahman Baseball Project</u>: Analysed the data for baseball player with highest salary and
  the team with the most wins in World championship. Have good exposure in managing the
  code in GitHub and using SQL CTE to create reports in Postgres.
- <u>Indian Start up</u>: Analyzed the data for the startups founded in India using Power BI.
   Worked individually to create different visuals to analyse various trends and growth in different sectors and also presented the dashboard to the larger audience.
- <u>Covid Impact on Medicare Population</u>: Imported data from CMS website to MS SQL Server.
   Created normalized tables in database and understood the data using CMS codebook.
   Worked on creating visualization on emotional impact on Medicare population due to Covid.Learnt to use tableau and presented the findings.

Jan 2022 – Present
[Career Break Feb 2017-Dec 2021]

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Anthem via Cognizant Technology Solutions

Anthem Inc., is a health insurance company in US, which works with providers to provide quality and affordable healthcare in the industry.

Project Lead Jun 2013 - Jan 2017 Technical Lead Apr 2009 - May 2013 Developer Dec 2006 - Mar 2009

- Having good understanding of the System through data analysis, trained team members to get knowledge on data model and end to end data flow across various stages in DW, which helped them to feel more confident about their work.
- Helped Business Users and Leadership team to get their answers related to production data by creating data reports using SQL on a timely basis. Due to large volume of inquiries and immense satisfaction on the reports ,the Leadership team approved to have large team size to handle huge data requests on a daily basis.
- Passion for data analysis, helped to analyse very complex scenarios such as to capture all the incremental changes for members of health insurance in the data warehouse source feed and deliver defect free code to production environment.
- Experience in creating dashboard presentation to report project status, defect metrics to the leadership team.
- Experience working with various teams such as Business Analyst team, Testing team, Production team, Development team and External team throughout Software Development Lifecycle.
- Ability to assist my project manager in planning monthly releases, resource management, work estimation and status reporting to Leadership team.

Dec 2006 - Jan 2017

# **EDUCATION & CERTIFICATIONS**

**Nashville Software School** 

Data Analytics Bootcamp Certification

Tagore Engineering College, Anna University, India

Bachelor of Engineering in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Expect. Grad.: April 2022

May 2006